Finding Aid for the Sephardic Temple Tifereth Israel Records LSC.2340
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject files, 1905-2014
  Series 3 contains subject files on certain individuals (most of whom were active members of STTI) and places of Jewish and/or Sephardic relevance, compiled by Maurice I. "Bob" Hattem (1919-2014) and his archival team. Some of Hattem's personal papers and research materials are included here. Of particular interest are the personal correspondence, including many letters in Ladino, that date as early 1911 and reach places like Izmir, New York, Jerusalem, Athens, and Los Angeles. This series also contains newspaper and journal clippings, as well as some published items.
  - Subseries 3.1: Maurice I. "Bob" Hattem papers, 1922-2005
    Sub-series 3.1 contains correspondence, research materials, and other personal documents of Maurice I. "Bob" Hattem. Hattem was the STTI archivist and editor of the temple's El Shofar monthly bulletin for many years. He was also active in Los Angeles, Southern California, and various Jewish, Crypto-Jewish, and Spanish historical societies.
    - Correspondence, 1980-2002 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Research, speeches, and other, 1970-2005 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Writings, 1980-2000 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Genealogical resources, 1990-2005 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Research materials, 1922-1999 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Research materials, 1972-2009 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Research materials, 1977-2004 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3.2: Personal files, 1911-2014
    Sub-series 3.2 contains documents by or about individuals connected to the Los Angeles Sephardic community. In addition to documents related to their lives in the temple, many files contain personal correspondence.
    - Eunice Pena Alisea, Maurice Amado, Richard Amado, Ralph S. Amado, 1930-1982 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Albert J. Amateau, 1983-1996 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Morris Angel, Hy Arnesty, 1981-2011 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Al Azus, Dr. Irving Benveniste, Art and Louis Benveniste, 1935-2003 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Cantor Isaac Behar, Victor Behar, Aronico Chico (alias of Harry J. Cohen), Isaac Cantos, Jack Cohen, 1920-1993 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Aron Cohen, 1946-1988 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Peter (Perahia) Alhadeff, 1933-1934, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Sue Halfon, Moshe Lazar, Leon Ligier, 1928-1987 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Leon Ligier manuscript, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 5-6)
    - Leon Ligier manuscript, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 1-2)
    - Cantor Haim Mizrahi, Jack Nehama, Rabbi Jacob Ott, 1954-2011 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Isaac Varon, 1932-1957 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Stella Rugetti, Irene Rugetti, 1951-1981 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Jack Seror, Haym Solomon Day, 1954-1988 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Nissim Saul and Sarah Reby letters, 1911-1915 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Nissim Saul and Sarah Reby letters, 1913-1944 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3.3: Place files, 1905-2003
    Sub-series 3.3 contains research materials collected by Bob Hattem and the archival team at STTI relating to places of Jewish and Sephardic interest, especially Spain.
    - Chinese Jews, Cuba, Egypt, Salonica (Greece), Rhodes (Greece), Greece, 1944-2003 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Holland, Israel, Mexico, 1947-1975 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      Holland section contains: Besso, Henry V. Dramatic Literature of the Sephardic Jews of Amsterdam in the XVIIth and XVIIIth Centuries. New York: Hispanic Institute in the United States, 1947.
    - Spain - Columbus, Spain - Girona, 1981-1992 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Spain - Inquisition and Expulsion, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      Contains: Raphael, David T. The Expulsion 1492 Chronicles: An Anthology of Medieval Chronicles Relating to the Expulsion of the Jews from Spain and Portugal. North Hollywood, Calif: Carmi House Press, 1992.
    - Spain - The Augustan Society, Spain Inquisition, 1983-1997 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Spain and Portugal travel guides, 1992-1997 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Spain - miscellaneous, 1970-1992 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Spain - Royal visit documents, 1951-2000 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Spain - Royal visit book, 1988 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Tunisia, Turkey, 1981-1992 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - United States of America, 1969-1990 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - California and Los Angeles, 1905-1991 (Box 41, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Photographs, scrapbooks, and clippings, circa 1910-2001
  Series 4 contains photographs and scrapbooks from STTI official events and functions, as well as those relating to individuals and families associated with the congregation. Labeling, condition, and type of photograph and scrapbook vary considerably - some are in excellent condition, while others fairly poor. While most items were produced in Los Angeles, several originate from New York or Seattle, and still others abroad. The scrapbooks in subseries 4.2 contain newspaper clippings from local, national, Jewish, and general publications over a considerable date range that relate to STTI or Los Angeles Sephardic life, featuring many from the local Jewish publication, B'nai B'rith Messenger.
  - Subseries 4.1: Photographs, 1910-2001
    Sub-series 4.1 contains photographs and negatives from Sephardic community affairs, events, and celebrations, as well as personal and family photographs from community members.
    - City of Hope, dignitaries, El Shofar Staff, Girona-Spain, 1940-1983 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Archives staff, board of directors, Israel bond drive, cantors, Veteran's Day committee, 1948-1991 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Sue Halfon dinner, past presidents, Sol Halfon estate, 1910-1992 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Holidays and events, Amateau, individuals, Leo Saul collection, 1930-1993 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Installations, Ladinos/Turkish night, LASHA, Los Merecidos award, Alliance Israelite Universelle, Mt. Sinai, 1980s events, musical events, 1934-1989 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Past presidents, rabbis, Sephardic brotherhood, Sephardic Hebrew Center, trip to Las Vegas, 1920-1990 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      Contains photo of Rabbi Jacob Ott with Governor Ronald Reagan, signed by the latter.
    - Board of directors, Mother's Day luncheon, sisterhood, TTI dedication, temple construction, 1930-1980 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Temple staff, Talmud Torah, United Jewish Welfare Fund, 1944-1989 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - STTI events, 1981-2001 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Los Merecidos award - Ted Negrin, 1990 (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Sisterhood Torah fund, bank breaking, 1985-1999 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Sisterhood Torah fund, officer installation, 1990-1999 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Sephardic Heritage Award Louis Alcalay, Al Azus, special award to Isaac R. Caraco, award to Carroll O'Connor, visit of California Senator Pete Wilson, 1980-1981, 1990 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Yehoram Gaon concert, 2000 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, Bar Mitzvah, banquets, awards, 1935-1985 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Youth synagogue, miscellaneous, loose captions, 1940-1991 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - STTI temple family album, 1930-1987 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Photograph slides: main sanctuary - old design, 1977 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Photographs: miscellaneous and unlabeled, 1930-1997 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      Contains black-and-white family and wedding photographs, some provided with names. Also contains: STTI past presidents, photograph of Haham Salomon Gaon, Dr. I. E. Benveniste, and Bob Hattem; STTI Archives Crew; Caraco-Varon wedding; Rabbi Bouskila Basketball team; Rabbi Ott with local political dignitaries; Albert Amateau 100th birthday party. Also includes a few unlabeled photographs from Greece.
    - Photographs: banquets, anniversaries, celebrations, 1925-1990 (Box 50)
    - Photographs: miscellaneous and unlabeled, past STTI presidents, 1919-1985 (Box 51)
      Several large photographs. Some include portraits of individuals like Caden Alhadeff, Bar Mitzvah classes, Talmud Torah, family photographs, and portraits of past STTI presidents.
      One item is a Sephardic Theater cast photo for the Queen Esther play performed in Ladino at Washington Hall on 14th and Fir, Seattle, WA, circa 1919. The play was directed by Rabbi Sabatai Israel of Izmir.
    - Negatives, 1920-1988 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Negatives of STTI events, past presidents, El Transito synagogue in Spain, some negatives donated by Joseph Moche.
    - Blown-up reproductions, 1932-1936 (Box 79)
  - Subseries 4.2: Scrapbooks and clippings, 1910-2004
    Subseries 4.2 contains various scrapbooks from STTI members and groups, such as the youth-oriented Juniors of Temple Tifereth Israel and the Ladinos group. These items contain photographs, newspaper clippings, letters, fliers, and other ephemera.
    - Miscellaneous STTI clippings, 1951-2000 (Box 46, Folder 5)
    - STTI scrapbook, 1950-1992 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - STTI scrapbook, 1950-1978 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - STTI scrapbook, 1979-1989 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook: Yolande Alcana Gross, 1957-1992 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook: Yolande Alcana Gross, 1969-1997 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Juniors of Temple Tifereth Israel (JTTI) reunion scrapbook, 1940-1990 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Ladinos scrapbook, 1931-1934 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Ladinos V yearbook, 1965-1966 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - The Ladinos scrapbook, 1966-1969 (Box 49)
    - The Ladinos scrapbook, 1970-1972 (Box 49)
    - Sisterhood scrapbook, 1935-1986 (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - Irene Rugeti, STTI Sisterhood president scrapbook, 1966-1968 (Box 52)
    - Jewish War Veterans scrapbook, Rabbi Jacob Ott album, 1910-2004 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Rabbi Jacob Ott scrapbook, 1946-1954 (Box 60)
    - Virginia Caraco Aldef scrapbook, 1957-1985 (Box 61)
- Series 5: Audiovisual, 1951-2004
  Series 5 contains audiovisual materials covering STTI events, such as lectures and cultural nights, interviews, live and studio music recordings, and a few commercial and other non-temple items.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. Please consult digital facsimiles instead of originals.
  - Subseries 5.1: Sene Collection, 1953-1980
    Subseries 5.1 contains lyric books collected by Emily Sene and 197 1/4 inch audiotapes. Most of these feature Isaac Sene singing and playing the oud alongside other musicians, recorded and notated by Emily Sene.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    - Sene lyric sheets, 1953-1980 (Box 48, Folder 4-6)
    - Sene lyric books, 1955-1977 (Box 53, Folder 1-3)
    - Sene audio reels, 1955-1977 (Box 62-68)
      Contains a total of 197, 1/4-inch audiotapes.
    - Sene reels inventory (Box 53, Folder 4)
      Other Finding Aids
      "A digital copy of the audiotapes inventory is available via this link: Link to Sephardic Temple records Sene audiotape inventory"
  - Subseries 5.2: Film, VHS, and audiocassettes, 1951-2004
    Subseries 5.2 contains 80 VHS tapes, 1 Betamax, and 93 audiocassettes of relevance to STTI, Sephardic, and Jewish life. Many of the VHS tapes are recordings of events held at STTI, as are the cassette recordings, while some are interviews or oral histories with individual community members. Some are commercial or professional recordings, while most are amateur recordings. Many of the items are of relevance to Sephardic history, culture, and music. A few audiocassettes in Box 58 feature Emily and Isaac Sene.
    - The End of the Night film, 1955; Film reel in fragile condition. (Box 69)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access to digital materials is available on-site in the Special Collections reading room. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance. Once request has been made, please confirm viewing arrangements with Special Collections reference desk staff.
      One reel of 16mm film.
      Documentary-dramatization film on the philanthropic efforts of the French-based Alliance Israelite Universelle on behalf of Jews in Morocco.
      Credits read as follows: Alliance Israelite Universelle presents an Omnium Franais du Film Production The End of the Night (Le Sixime Jour) Copyright 1955 by Omnium Franais du Film with Serge Baty and The Inhabitants of the Village of Illigh, South Morocco Cameraman Paul Fabian Film Editors Georges Alepee, Denise Charven Sound Engineer Paul Boistelle English commentary and dialogue written by Sidney Shelley Music by Josepha Kosma Written, Produced and Directed by Jean-Claude Huisman
      Existence and Location of Copies
      A digital reproduction of the film is available on-site in the Special Collections reading room.
    - VHS tapes, 1989-2004 (Box 54-56)
      Contains 80 VHS tapes and one Betamax, mostly of amateur recordings of STTI events in the 1990s but also includes some copies of documentaries of Sephardic interest.
      A digital copy of VHS inventory is available via this link: Link to Sephardic Temple records VHS inventory
    - Audiocassettes, 1951-2003 (Box 57-59)
      Contains 93 audiocassettes of interviews, lectures, performances from STTI and its members, as well as a few commercial recordings.
      A digital copy of audiocassettes inventory is available via this link: Link to Sephardic Temple records audiocassette inventory
- Series 6: Awards, artwork, and ephemera, 1911-2003
  Series 6 contains several certificates, awards, artwork, renderings, plaques, and commemorative items related to STTI and associated individuals.
  - Subseries 6.1: Awards, plaques, certificates, and drawings, 1911-2002
    Subseries 6.1 contains a range of awards, honors, certificates, plaques, commemorations, and related documents of relevance to the Sephardic Community, its groups and efforts, and its individual members. Several are from Los Angeles city, county, and California state official bodies. This subseries also contains some drawings, designs, and artwork related to the temple.
    - Plaques and awards, 1956-1984 (Box 72)
    - Plaques and awards, 1955-1991 (Box 76)
      Includes framed letter on behalf of President Richard Nixon honoring Rabbi Jacob Ott on receiving the Sephardic Heritage Award in 1971. Includes signed photo of President Richard Nixon.
    - Honors and certificates, 1931-2002 (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Jewish National Fund plaque, 1964 (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - Morris Passy Ottoman Birth certificate and Abraham Caraco rabbinic certificate, 1911-1912 (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Watercolor designs for sanctuary (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Temple Board caricature, circa 1950s (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - United Jewish Appeal commemorative medals, Ted Hasson award and key, 1963-1966 (Box 77)
    - Daily Prayer of Maimonides plaque, gift of King of Spain, 1987 (Box 78)
    - Oversize key - "Sephardic Community of LA, Feb 21, 1932" (Box 81)
    - Artist's rendering of STTI, STTI architectural plans, 1921 photocopy of Peace and Progress picnic, Marilyn Simon drawings, 1921-1990 (Box 83)
  - Subseries 6.2: Ephemera, 1913-2012
    Sub-series 6.2 contains various ephemera in the STTI records, including Bob Hattem's archival index cards and Jewish calendars from Turkey.
    - Archival index notecards, undated, likely 1980s (Box 73-74)
    - Fez, photocopy of Megilat Saragossa (Box 80)
    - Life-cycle event prayer booklets, 1986-2012 (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - Turkish Jewish calendars, 1966-1968 (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - The California Jewish Voice, 1947-1949 (Box 70, Folder 8)
      Includes: Vol. 26, No 13 (December 5, 1947); Vol. 26, No. 36 (May 14, 1948); Vol, 26, No. 44 (July 9, 1948); Vol. 27, No. 35 (May 9, 1949)